<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Let quilibet beware of quodlibet</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20562</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103455</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839208</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839208</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3610</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10280)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3610)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1253:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Let quilibet beware of quodlibet</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: pi¹ A (-A6-8).</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Answers STC 25123: William Watson. A decacordon of ten quodlibeticall questions concerning religion and state, published in 1602.</note>
                  <note>Some pages marked.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Watson, William, 1559?-1603. --  Decacordon of ten quodlibeticall questions.</term>
               <term>Watson, William, 1559?-1603. --  A decacordon of ten quodlibetical questions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3610:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3610:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LET QVILIBET <hi>BEWARE OF</hi> QVODLIBET.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3610:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the true Engliſh harted reader.</head>
            <p>Whereas the right Hon. the L. Keeper, ſignified in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uild hall, that ſome In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vaſion was pretended by the spaniard, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeing it might be againſt <hi>England,</hi> Her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie (according to her motherly and princely care) is minded to prepare forces accordingly. It is therefore neceſſary, that the state were made acquainted with thoſe dangerous, ſediti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous, and treaſonable poynts, which (vnder the pretence of contention betweene ſecular prieſts and I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſuits) are publiſhed, To prepare papiſts to rebellion. Some few whereof are here collected and ſett d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wne in the prieſts their owne words the ſhort notes vpon ſome of them beinge print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a different letter.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:3610:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>LET QVILIBET, BEVVARE OF QVODLIBET.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>To omitt their often and greivous charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Church with hereſy and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Let vs wiſlye (to prevent a miſcheife) exa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myne their dealeinge with our state, for they are not a fraid to write as followeth. viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Execution of Iuſtice ſlaundred:</p>
            <p n="1">1 It is true that towards the number of 50 Priſts &amp; Catholiques of all ſorts with in the compaſſe of 10. yeares (<hi>meaneing from</hi> 80. <hi>to</hi> 90.) were put to death we ſay vpon our knowledges
<hi>(concerning the moſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>)</hi> for their conſciences but our aduerſaries affirme for treaſon. Important conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons page. 29. line. 21.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They <hi>(ſpeakeing of wiſemen)</hi> caſt their eyes a ſide, to Turkes, to Perſians, and to all pagan provinces, to ſee if they can eſpye any one ſect, profeſſion, or profeſſors of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion, toſſed, turmoyled, and tormented, as the Engliſh are, &amp; through all this waſt Macrocoſme, they finde not one patterne or example left to poſterity to be recorded like ours. Quodlibets pag. 274. line.
33.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The afliction of Catholiques in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land hath bine indeede very extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and many an innocent man hath loſt
<pb facs="tcp:3610:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>his life. Quod. pag 276. line
37.</p>
            <p>Authoritie of the Parliament <hi>diminiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 The <hi>5.</hi> ſtatue there made <hi>(speakeing of a parliament held by Ieſuits)</hi> was concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing calumniation, not much vnlike that ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Aſſociation. Quod p. 95. l. 10. <hi>Note that Aſſociation enacted is ſcornefully compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red. The reaſon is evident. To witt becauſe it bindeth faithfull ſubiects to ſett themſelus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch competitors, as ſhall attempt any thinge againſt the Queene or, state.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 If Princes ſhould take from the Church all temporall poſſeſſions, it would little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, to bringe in our diſtinctions. How parliaments may giue what they liſt to the Church, and churchmen, but they can take nothinge from them or the church Quod. pag. 294. l. 24. <hi>Note that it is ſaide our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinctions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Popes authoritye advanced <hi>aboue her Maieſties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>It being affirmed, that</hi> A premunire was incurred, and treaſon vpon treaſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, in procuring the Archprieſts autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity from the Pope, yet the prieſts their ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peale to the Pope, <hi>is iuſtified for theſe (amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g other reaſons)</hi> 1. To whom the Iniurye is <pb facs="tcp:3610:3"/>done, to him the right of revenge doth ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crewe: But the Popes holines was iniured by the Ieſuites their ſuggeſtions in obtayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing that authoritye, ergo. <hi>As if her Maieſtie were not hereby iniured.</hi> 2. The Ieſuits in procuring that authority: made it a matter of ſtate, but the ſeculars in appealing made it a matter of conſcience. <hi>As if the Pope had in matters of conſcience authority aboue her Maieſtie.</hi> 3 Ieſuits boulſter out that autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and theire treaſonable practiſes vpon his holines authority ergo, none other to appeale to, for Iuſtice againſt them. <hi>As though the Queene had not authority to iudge treaſonable practiſes of Ieſuits.</hi> Quod. page 171 line 13.</p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>The Seculars being charged with ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, to cleare themſelues do thus ſay,</hi> All ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale is intrinſically an acknowledgeing of authority, in the higheſt degree to the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty appealed vnto. Anſwere to a Ieſuited gentleman p. 24. l. 1. <hi>But they Seculars ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to the Pope: ergo they acknowledge his authority in the higheſt degree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 I know that (iure eccleſiaſtico, and by authority and ſentence of the Popes holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) much more may be done than I will heere ſpeake off. But yet I thinke it will proue (in the ende) the beſt courſe for men <pb facs="tcp:3610:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>not to doe ſo much as they may. Many things are lawfull <hi>(viz. Excommunication of Princes)</hi> which are not expedient in this ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riligious and moſt vnfortunat age Quod. pag 293. line 27. and pag 158. line 21.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Vnto the writings not only of Parſons but of Thomas</hi> Aquinas <hi>alſo, and other ſcholemen, and learned Papiſts. All avouching that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects</hi> may and ought depoſe <hi>Princes with holding popiſhe religion, if they had force en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough, it is thus anſwered.</hi> Loe what doctrine is this to be divulged in this ſo dangerous an age, I leaue to others to conceipt theſe thinges in as good ſence as may make for our generall ſafety, and common good of the Catholique cauſe. Quod. pa. 296. l. 34. <hi>Soe that it appeareth, how cuningly prieſts would wright this doctrine, in the hartes of their proſelites, by them to be practiſed, when they may haue hope to prevaile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>Haueing moſt impudently affirmed that</hi> Pius Quintus <hi>his Bull was called in againe (whereas the truth is, that</hi> Gregorie 13. <hi>was only content, that it ſhould not binde papiſts: who durſt not but iobey her Maieſties lawes, vpon c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndition they ſhould rebell when time might ſerue, but her Maieſtie was left excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated) here</hi> VVatſon <hi>the prieſt and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <pb facs="tcp:3610:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the</hi> Quodlibets, <hi>diſcouereth himſelfe in theſe words:</hi> Amongeſt many examples of the fatherly compaſſion of the Popes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, towards the inhabitants and princes of this land, in times of eminent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthes danger, the cheife (ſince the Norma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt) was ſhewed in the reignes of Kinge Hen. the 2 &amp; his ſonne K. Iohn. Againſt whom haueing vſed his fatherlye correction (as Paſtor vniuerſall over the whole flocke of Chriſt, for their great tiran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny vſed towards their naturall ſubiects, yet vpon repentance etc. Surrendered vp the crowne of England to Kinge Iohn and his heires and ſucceſſors, from off the head of Cardinall Pandulphus, who had ſit inthro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nized 3 dayes theirwith, in the popes right. Thowſands there are in England which de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſire as much, and wilbe ready to lay theire liues to pledg for it, that if any Lancaſtrian forrenner ſhall gett poſſeſſion of this land, yet would this Pope Clement the 8 (accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to his predeceſſors example) revoke and force him, or her, to retire, and withall wovld of his meere mercy (a gift appropri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ated to S. Peters chaire) graunt to our nati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, to chuſe a Kinge of our owne natiue ſoyle, vpon like ſubmiſſion of former prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in this, and other kingdomes. Qoud.
<pb facs="tcp:3610:5"/>327. l. 24. <hi>Note what authority to the Pope is attributed, and what ſubmiſſion of our ſtat is required.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 VVe wiſh with al our harts (&amp; groane every day at the contrary) that her Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, had continued in her obeydience, to the ſea apoſtolique as Q. Mary her ſiſter (of famous memory) had left her a worthy example Import. conſi. pag 5. l. 3.</p>
            <p n="12">12 They labour by their appeale, for ſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rety to her Maieſties perſon, for quyet to the ſtate, for avoydance of all invaſions, for cutting off all conſperacyes, ſtate tamper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, &amp; exaſperating libels, &amp; for aſſurance of freedome from their heavie perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Quod. p. 171 l. 27: <hi>As if theſe thinges could not be without their appeale, but if this be not preiudiciall to her Maieſtie and state, what is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alteration of ſtate conceined.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 Their witts <hi>(meaneing prieſts &amp; papiſts)</hi> being occupied with conceites of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes (viz. Eaſe and ſecuritie) makes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one wiſh in their hartes for a change. Quod. pag 152. line 27.</p>
            <p n="13">13 This land aſwell by the ſuppreſſion of Abbies as by ſundry other dangers wherin it ſtands, eſpecially by popular doctrine of <pb facs="tcp:3610:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ieſuits, is brought to ly open to the ſpoyle of who that firſt can catch it Quod. p.
186. line 11. <hi>Note this ſeditious giueing of hope to traitors and Invadours, but withall examine that popular doctrine which is this, and ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the margent where it is ſet downe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 By this <hi>(meaneing a poynt of Ieſuitiſme)</hi> the popular multitude may depoſe theire princes and chuſe others at their pleaſure, By this no difference ſhalbe put in theire choiſe, vpon any right or title to crownes, or kingdomes, by byrth or blood, or other wyſe than as the father (forſooth) ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue it, by this althings muſt be wrought, and framed, conformable to the oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of tymes and occaſions as verba gratia. they people haue a right &amp; intereſt in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to doe what they liſt in choyſe of a kinge: marry yet lymitted by reaſon, of the times occaſions now offered to one of theſe two, the Kinge of Spayne or the Lady Infanta. And then againe the tymes and occaſions changing, after a Spaniard is ſettled in the crowne, it muſt be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a miſtakeing, yet ſuch, as ſeeing it cannot be holpen, the people muſt beware hereafter, of ever at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting the like againe by this a checke muſt be giuen to the publiſhers of ſuch pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes. <pb facs="tcp:3610:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>After that a diſpenſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> procured for reſtoreinge the offendor, and then all ſhalbe well everafter. Quod. page 68. l. 11. <hi>Here remember the ſeculars opinion of chuſinge a Kinge of our owne nation ſett downe in the end of the</hi> 10 <hi>article, and if you find it to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer but a little (if any thinge) from the Ieſuits opinion, touchinge the authority of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude etc, then conſider whether the Prieſts doe not conſpire with the Ieſuits as in a conceipt of alteringe the ſtate, ſo in takeinge a courſe to bringe their purpoſe to paſſe, which muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trolled after their purpoſe is effected. viz. In their politique inveighing againſt Ieſuits alreae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy in diſgrace, theirby to draw our stat in hope of mainteineyng a ſuppoſed contention to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour them, that by their proceedinge practiſe may (in time) bringe in popery againe, as fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appeareth in the</hi> 17 <hi>article.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16 The many libertyes, free education, and great wealth of nobles, gentlemen and other ſubiects co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered, eſpecially, In that an Engliſh nature, even in the meaneſt member of the body politicall (ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>il. in the comminalty) is in this reſpect noble, free of highe courage, and not able to endure lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering deathes, torments, guſtes &amp; greifes, as other people are, that notwithſtanding <pb facs="tcp:3610:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſubiectes, as well noble as ignoble, ſhould ſhould be put to thoſe exigents, that catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques haue bene a long time put vnto: the world hath muſed and admired at it <hi>Quod</hi> page 270. line 30. <hi>Is not this an inſtigation to rebellion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17 The latter doth vrge againſt the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer (viz. Ieſuits againſt ſeculars) that it is their falt if they be not of ſtrength enough. For if <hi>all</hi> would ſlyde one way: they are a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to match their adverſaries at al aſſayes. <hi>Quod.</hi> pag 208. line 20
<hi>Here we perceiue the Ieſuits mynd: with whom moſt papiſtes are ſaide to concurr: let vs now marke and conſider they prieſts their opinion and purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>n8. If we our ſelues, within our ſelues, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh religion: why may not we our ſelues, within our ſelues, by the proceeding prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Seminaries: bringe it in againe, the peoteſtant being now no more vnlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be a voyded, than the catholique was then. <hi>Anſ. to a Ieſuited gent.</hi> pag. 54. lin. 31. &amp; p. 66. <hi>l.</hi> 28. <hi>Doth it not appeare that change of religion is one: and the ſame end of prieſts and Ieſuits: their wicked practiſes? But read: and conſider what is acknowledge viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſpiracy of prieſts &amp; Ieſuits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. All mainteineyng <hi>(speakeing of papiſts in generall)</hi> one and the ſame opinion: con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerninge what might be done by a poſtoli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cal <pb facs="tcp:3610:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>authority and power: and neuer talke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng what is neceſſary. <hi>Quod.</hi> p. 277.
<hi>li.</hi> 17. <hi>Whereby it is evident, that howſoever Prieſts &amp; Ieſuits ſeeme otherwiſe to diſgrace: yet here in they iumpe: That her Maieſtie is to be held lawfully excommunicated by the Pope: when it ſhalbe expedient ſo to doe. But let this full confeſſion following be diligently conſidered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20 The Seminaries were willinge at the firſt to couler hyde, and conceale all, make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ieſuits cauſe, attempts, intends prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes their owne in every thinge, vntill at laſt they were intangled by penall lawes. pag 6. line 25 of the preface to the Quod.</p>
            <p n="21">21 <hi>Lastly it is to be noted, that howſoever the ſeculars doe grevoſly charge the Ieſuits, &amp; other (executed for the ſame) with horrible trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons &amp; fellonies, denyed in other popiſh bookes, yet (in the end) they conclude thus.</hi> VVhatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is written or contained in theſe bookes we ſubmit all to the cenſure and Iudgment of our holy mother the catholique Romain Church Import. conſi. pag 43. &amp; Quod. p. 361. lin 12. <hi>which doth imply, that Papiſtes knowes theſe traitorous bookes to be written a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt Ieſuits but of policye, &amp; that prieſts are ready to vnſay all, when the Pope ſhall either requyre the ſame, or els, pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thoſe treaſons and felonies, to be holy practiſes of popiſh zeale, where of more is ſaid in the</hi> 15.
<hi>article.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3610:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
